Chapter 5. Building Blocks


The last chapter explored several techniques for constructing thread-safe classes, including delegating thread safety to existing thread-safe classes. Where practical, delegation is one of the most effective strategies for creating thread-safe classes: just let existing thread-safe classes manage all the state.

The platform libraries include a rich set of concurrent building blocks, such as thread-safe collections and a variety of synchronizers that can coordinate the control flow of cooperating threads. This chapter covers the most useful concurrent building blocks, especially those introduced in Java 5.0 and Java 6, and some patterns for using them to structure concurrent applications.

5.1. Synchronized Collections

The synchronized collection classes include Vector and Hashtable, part of the original JDK, as well as their cousins added in JDK 1.2, the synchronized wrapper classes created by the Collections.synchronizedXxx factory methods. These classes achieve thread safety by encapsulating their state and synchronizing every public method so that only one thread at a time can access the collection state.

5.1.1. Problems with Synchronized Collections

The synchronized collections are thread-safe, but you may sometimes need to use additional client-side locking to guard compound actions. Common compound actions on collections include iteration (repeatedly fetch elements until the collection is exhausted), navigation (find the next element after this one according to some order), and conditional operations such as put-if-absent (check if a Map has a mapping for key K, and if not, add the mapping (K,V)). With a synchronized collection, these compound actions are still technically thread-safe even without client-side locking, but they may not behave as you might expect when other threads can concurrently modify the collection.

Listing 5.1 shows two methods that operate on a Vector, getLast and delete-Last, both of which are check-then-act sequences. Each calls size to determine the size of the array and uses the resulting value to retrieve or remove the last element.

Listing 5.1. Compound Actions on a Vector that may Produce Confusing Results.


public static Object getLast(Vector list) {
    int lastIndex = list.size() - 1;
    return list.get(lastIndex);
}

public static void deleteLast(Vector list) {
    int lastIndex = list.size() - 1;
    list.remove(lastIndex);
}

These methods seem harmless, and in a sense they are—they can’t corrupt the Vector, no matter how many threads call them simultaneously. But the caller of these methods might have a different opinion. If thread A calls getLast on a Vector with ten elements, thread B calls deleteLast on the same Vector, and the operations are interleaved as shown in Figure 5.1, getLast throws ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException. Between the call to size and the subsequent call to get in getLast, the Vector shrank and the index computed in the first step is no longer valid. This is perfectly consistent with the specification of Vector—it throws an exception if asked for a nonexistent element. But this is not what a caller expects getLast to do, even in the face of concurrent modification, unless perhaps the Vector was empty to begin with.

Figure 5.1. Interleaving of Getlast and Deletelast that throws ArrayIndexOut-OfBoundsException.




Because the synchronized collections commit to a synchronization policy that supports client-side locking, [1] it is possible to create new operations that are atomic with respect to other collection operations as long as we know which lock to use. The synchronized collection classes guard each method with the lock on the synchronized collection object itself. By acquiring the collection lock we can make getLast and deleteLast atomic, ensuring that the size of the Vector does not change between calling size and get, as shown in Listing 5.2.

[1] This is documented only obliquely in the Java 5.0 Javadoc, as an example of the correct iteration idiom.

The risk that the size of the list might change between a call to size and the corresponding call to get is also present when we iterate through the elements of a Vector as shown in Listing 5.3.

This iteration idiom relies on a leap of faith that other threads will not modify the Vector between the calls to size and get. In a single-threaded environment, this assumption is perfectly valid, but when other threads may concurrently modify the Vector it can lead to trouble. Just as with getLast, if another thread deletes an element while you are iterating through the Vector and the operations are interleaved unluckily, this iteration idiom throws ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException.

* idiom 英['ɪdɪəm] 美['ɪdɪəm] n. 成语，习语；土话
* leap 英[liːp] 美[lip] vi. 跳，跳跃 n. 飞跃；跳跃
* faith 英[feɪθ] 美[feθ] n. 信仰；信念；信任；忠实
* A Leap of Faith飞跃的信心；信任度的提高
* interleave 英[ɪntə'liːv] 美[,ɪntɚ'liv] vt. [计] 交错；插空白页于；插叙 n. [计] 交错

Listing 5.2. Compound Actions on Vector Using Client-side Locking.

public static Object getLast(Vector list) {
    synchronized (list) {
        int lastIndex = list.size() - 1;
        return list.get(lastIndex);
    }
}

public static void deleteLast(Vector list) {
    synchronized (list) {
        int lastIndex = list.size() - 1;
        list.remove(lastIndex);
    }
}

Listing 5.3. Iteration that may Throw ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException.

for (int i = 0; i < vector.size(); i++)
    doSomething(vector.get(i));

Even though the iteration in Listing 5.3 can throw an exception, this doesn’t mean Vector isn’t thread-safe. The state of the Vector is still valid and the exception is in fact in conformance with its specification. However, that something as mundane as fetching the last element or iteration throw an exception is clearly undesirable.

The problem of unreliable iteration can again be addressed by client-side locking, at some additional cost to scalability. By holding the Vector lock for the duration of iteration, as shown in Listing 5.4, we prevent other threads from modifying the Vector while we are iterating it. Unfortunately, we also prevent other threads from accessing it at all during this time, impairing concurrency.

* conformance 英[kən'fɔːm(ə)ns] 美[kən'fɔrməns] n. 一致性；顺应
* mundane 英['mʌndeɪn; mʌn'deɪn] 美[mʌn'den] adj. 世俗的，平凡的；世界的，宇宙的
* scalability 英[,skeilə'biliti] 美 n. 可扩展性；可伸缩性；可量测性
* impair 英[ɪm'peə] 美[ɪm'pɛr] vt. 损害；削弱；减少




Listing 5.4. Iteration with Client-side Locking.

synchronized (vector) {
    for (int i = 0; i < vector.size(); i++)
        doSomething(vector.get(i));
}

5.1.2. Iterators and Concurrentmodificationexception

We use Vector for the sake of clarity in many of our examples, even though it is considered a “legacy” collection class. But the more “modern” collection classes do not eliminate the problem of compound actions. The standard way to iterate a Collection is with an Iterator, either explicitly or through the for-each loop syntax introduced in Java 5.0, but using iterators does not obviate the need to lock the collection during iteration if other threads can concurrently modify it. The iterators returned by the synchronized collections are not designed to deal with concurrent modification, and they are fail-fast—meaning that if they detect that the collection has changed since iteration began, they throw the unchecked ConcurrentModificationException.

* sake 英[seɪk] 美[sek] n. 目的；利益；理由；日本米酒
** for the sake of 为了；为了…的利益
* clarity 英['klærɪtɪ] 美['klærəti] n. 清楚，明晰；透明
* eliminate 英[ɪ'lɪmɪneɪt] 美[ɪ'lɪmɪnet] vt. 消除；排除
* obviate 英['ɒbvɪeɪt] 美['ɑbvɪet] vt. 排除；避免；消除



These fail-fast iterators are not designed to be foolproof—they are designed to catch concurrency errors on a “good-faith-effort” basis and thus act only as early-warning indicators for concurrency problems. They are implemented by associating a modification count with the collection: if the modification count changes during iteration, hasNext or next throws ConcurrentModificationException. However, this check is done without synchronization, so there is a risk of seeing a stale value of the modification count and therefore that the iterator does not realize a modification has been made. This was a deliberate design tradeoff to reduce the performance impact of the concurrent modification detection code.[2]

* stale 报错 英[steɪl] 美[stel] adj. 陈腐的；不新鲜的 vi. 变陈旧；撒尿；变得不新鲜 vt. 使变旧；变得不新鲜
* deliberate 报错 英[dɪ'lɪb(ə)rət] 美[dɪ'lɪbərət] adj. 故意的；深思熟虑的；从容的 vt. 仔细考虑；商议


[2] ConcurrentModificationException can arise in single-threaded code as well; this happens when objects are removed from the collection directly rather than through Iterator.remove.

Listing 5.5 illustrates iterating a collection with the for-each loop syntax. Internally, javac generates code that uses an Iterator, repeatedly calling hasNext and next to iterate the List. Just as with iterating the Vector, the way to prevent ConcurrentModificationException is to hold the collection lock for the duration of the iteration.

Listing 5.5. Iterating a List with an Iterator.


List<Widget> widgetList
    = Collections.synchronizedList(new ArrayList<Widget>());
...
// May throw ConcurrentModificationException
for (Widget w : widgetList)
    doSomething(w);

There are several reasons, however, why locking a collection during iteration may be undesirable. Other threads that need to access the collection will block until the iteration is complete; if the collection is large or the task performed for each element is lengthy, they could wait a long time. Also, if the collection is locked as in Listing 5.4, doSomething is being called with a lock held, which is a risk factor for deadlock (see Chapter 10). Even in the absence of starvation or deadlock risk, locking collections for significant periods of time hurts application scalability. The longer a lock is held, the more likely it is to be contended, and if many threads are blocked waiting for a lock throughput and CPU utilization can suffer (see Chapter 11).

An alternative to locking the collection during iteration is to clone the collection and iterate the copy instead. Since the clone is thread-confined, no other thread can modify it during iteration, eliminating the possibility of ConcurrentModificationException. (The collection still must be locked during the clone operation itself.) Cloning the collection has an obvious performance cost; whether this is a favorable tradeoff depends on many factors including the size of the collection, how much work is done for each element, the relative frequency of iteration compared to other collection operations, and responsiveness and throughput requirements.

* obvious 报错 英['ɒbvɪəs] 美['ɑbvɪəs] adj. 明显的；显著的；平淡无奇的
* responsiveness 报错 英 美[rɪ'spɑnsɪvnɪs] n. 响应能力；有同情心
* throughput 报错 英['θruːpʊt] 美['θrʊ'pʊt] n. 生产量，生产能力


5.1.3. Hidden Iterators

While locking can prevent iterators from throwing ConcurrentModificationException, you have to remember to use locking everywhere a shared collection might be iterated. This is trickier than it sounds, as iterators are sometimes hidden, as in HiddenIterator in Listing 5.6. There is no explicit iteration in HiddenIterator, but the code in bold entails iteration just the same. The string concatenation gets turned by the compiler into a call to StringBuilder.append(Object), which in turn invokes the collection’s toString method—and the implementation of toString in the standard collections iterates the collection and calls toString on each element to produce a nicely formatted representation of the collection’s contents.

* trickier 报错 adj. 狡猾的；机警的 (tricky的变形)
* concatenation 报错 英[kənkætə'neɪʃn] 美[kən'kætə'neʃən] n. 串联，连结
* entail 报错 英[ɪn'teɪl; en-] 美[ɪn'tel] vt. 使需要，必需；承担；遗传给；蕴含 n. 引起；需要；继承



The addTenThings method could throw ConcurrentModificationException, because the collection is being iterated by toString in the process of preparing the debugging message. Of course, the real problem is that HiddenIterator is not thread-safe; the HiddenIterator lock should be acquired before using set in the println call, but debugging and logging code commonly neglect to do this.

The real lesson here is that the greater the distance between the state and the synchronization that guards it, the more likely that someone will forget to use proper synchronization when accessing that state. If HiddenIterator wrapped the HashSet with a synchronizedSet, encapsulating the synchronization, this sort of error would not occur.

Just as encapsulating an object’s state makes it easier to preserve its invariants, encapsulating its synchronization makes it easier to enforce its synchronization policy.


Listing 5.6. Iteration Hidden within String Concatenation. Don’t Do this.


public class HiddenIterator {
    @GuardedBy("this")
    private final Set<Integer> set = new HashSet<Integer>();

    public synchronized void add(Integer i) { set.add(i); }
    public synchronized void remove(Integer i) { set.remove(i); }

    public void addTenThings() {
        Random r = new Random();
        for (int i = 0; i < 10; i++)
            add(r.nextInt());
        System.out.println("DEBUG: added ten elements to " + set);
   }
}

Iteration is also indirectly invoked by the collection’s hashCode and equals methods, which may be called if the collection is used as an element or key of another collection. Similarly, the containsAll, removeAll, and retainAll methods, as well as the constructors that take collections as arguments, also iterate the collection. All of these indirect uses of iteration can cause ConcurrentModificationException.
